If you are currently
thinking of taking a health insurance plan, then there must be a confusion in your mind
whether to take Nima Bupa's
latest plan Reshore 3.0 or
HDFC ARGO's Optima Secure plan which is
already very popular and
is also the best selling plan in the market.  In today's
video we will do a fair comparison between these two plans.  First of all, you will
know
which of these two plans you are
eligible to take.  We will discuss those conditions.
Then we will compare the
coverage and benefits so that we
can check which plan offers you better features.
We will also know which plan has better add-ons and when it comes to
premium, we will also check the affordability to see
which plan will be cheaper for you in the long run
and most importantly, after analyzing the claims data, we will know
which of these two companies is better in terms of claims.
So if you are also
confused between these two plans, then
this video will clear all your confusion.
So come on, what are you waiting for?   Let's
start this video quickly.  If you
want to take HDFC Ergo Optima Secure plan, the minimum
entry age for adults is 18 years and there is no capping on the maximum age.
But if there is a
dependent child in your family.
Dependent child means your children who are
still non-earning, do not have any income of their
own and are also unmarried, i.e. they are
not married, then as a dependent
child they can come under your family floater policy.
Their minimum entry age is 91
years and maximum age will be 25 years.  If we
talk about Reshore 3.0 plan, the
minimum entry age for adults is 18 years and the
maximum age is 99 years.  You can say there is no
capping.  The age of the dependent child is
given a little higher here.
Dependent children can remain part
of a floater policy along with their parents for a period ranging from 91 days to 30 years.
If we talk about
renewal, that is,
how long can you run this policy once you have purchased it, then there is
no age limit for it.  You can
continue both these plans for life long.
How many types of plans can you take
?  So here, individual plan means
separate sum insured for each member, you
can take a plan for yourself alone and you
can also take a family floater policy in which there is a
common sum insured for the entire family
and any member can use the money from that sum insured for treatment.  Both
these options are available in both the plans.
Now the major difference comes in the sum insured
i.e. how much coverage you will
get under these plans.  If we talk about HDFC
Ergo Optima Secure plan, then the minimum
sum insured is ₹5 lakh and the maximum sum
insured will be ₹2 crore, but
this time the company has done something new in the Neem Upay Reshore 3.0 plan.
Two sum insured options of ₹5 lakh and ₹1 lakh are given and the third
option is unlimited sum insured.   Yes,
you understood it correctly.  Unlimited
means that there will be no limit on your treatment expenses.
So this hassle of taking a plan of Rs
25 lakh, 50 lakh, 1 crore is over.  If you
take unlimited sum insured then
that tension will be over.  Now let's talk about
tenure.  That is, for how long can you
buy a long term policy at one go.
For example, we buy a 3-year policy
so that if there is any premium revision in future or
inflation increases, it does not affect us
and we also get some discount.  So,
under HDFC & Optima Secure plan,
you will get a long term policy of 3 years.
But in Reader 3.0 plan you can
also get a long term policy of 5 years.  It is also
important to know how many variants are there in both the plans.
Because we can
also choose the right variant according to our need.
So, there
is only one variant in the Optima Secure plan, Optima
Secure.  But if you buy a 3 year long
term policy then this plan becomes
super secure.  In which you get
not two times but three times secure benefit
from the very first day.  Whereas there are a
total of four variants within the Ratio 3.0 plan
which have been differentiated on the basis of different features.  The
most basic
variant is the Classic then the less Select.
Next is Elite and the top variant is Black.
You will find capping within the lower two variants of the overall coverage theme adopted by NVPA.  Be it room rent,
modern treatments, ambulance
charges, there you will
get capping in lower two variants, you will
get subvention.  But the top two variants are
Elite and Black, there are
no supplements in Black.
You may notice some gaping here and there inside the Elite.
Now friends, let's talk about the
USP of both the plans.  That is,
what are the best features of both these plans which
make these plans very attractive.
You have seen the videos of Optima Secure Plan many times.  But still let
us discuss its USP again.  The
first benefit
is secure benefit.  Secure benefit
means that if I buy a policy of ₹1 lakh today,
then on the very first day I
am eligible for a claim of ₹1 lakh i.e. two times it.
That's why the name of the plan is Optima Secure.
Next Comes Plus Benefit.  Plus Benefit
is a kind of cumulative bonus that the company
offers you in the Optima Secure plan.
Irrespective of claim.  You
will get a cumulative bonus of 50% on the first renewal.
50% off on next renewal.  Similarly,
after two renewals,
you accumulate more money equal to your sum insured.
Third Comes Protect Benefit.   The
Protect benefit
provides coverage for your non-medical items.  Which we
also call consumables.  Such as gloves,
syringe, cotton.  Such huge expenses can occur
in any treatment.  But
you get coverage for these through the Protect benefit within the base variant of the Optima Secure plan itself.
But keep one thing in
mind that under this
you get coverage only for 68 non-medical items of Anxure B.
Now friends let's talk about
some USB of NVP roses 3.0.  So their first and
unique feature is unlimited sum
insured.  Earlier there was a lot of confusion as to
how many times should I revise the sum insured?
20 lakhs, 25 lakhs, 50 lakhs.  So the company said that
you should take unlimited sum insured only.  This
hassle will end.  There is a cumulative bonus of restoration,
recharge benefit or in addition to it.
This concept itself will end.
Unlimited sum insured,
get treatment as long as you need it.  There
is no limit on your sum insured.  The second
USP is the lock the clock benefit.  We are very
worried about the revision of premium
and one of the biggest reasons for this is the
revision of premium with age.  But
in the top two variants of Ratio 3.0 i.e. Alt and Black, you get the Lock the
Clock feature which you have already seen in Ratio 2.0 and
Aspire plan.  If
I have taken a policy today at the age of 25 years
and I do not make any claim for the next
10-15 years, then my age-specific premium will
not be revised.  That means the premium which increases with age band will
not increase.  Then
whatever age I file a claim at, the
premium for that age will become applicable in future.
This is also a very good feature.   The
third USP is coverage of 145 pre-existing
diseases from day one.  That means there are some
listed medical conditions for which
you can get coverage from day one under the Reor 3.0 plan.
But there are some conditions in this, that is, the
underwriters of the company, that is, the decision
makers, will check whether they provide this coverage to
you or not.  Secondly, if he
allows coverage for any pre-existing medical condition from day one, then the
company will definitely charge money for it.  So loadings will
definitely be applicable to this.  Apart from this,
if your sum insured is a fixed amount of ₹
5 lakh and ₹1 lakh, which are the only two options,
in any variant you take, then you
also get Booster Plus benefit, that is,
whatever unutilized sum insured you have,
you can carry forward it up to 10 times and
along with this you also get Reshore Forever which is
their recharge benefit.
After being triggered on the first claim, this amount will be
available for life time up to 100% of the sum
insured and for unlimited times in a
policy year.  Now friends, let's talk about some
such features which are common but which are
very important to discuss.  The first point
is the room rent limit, that is,
which category of room can we take during treatment
in both these plans.  There is no
capping or limit on room rent in Optima Secure plan.
But the top variant of the Ratio 3.0 plan,
Black, does
not have any sublimit or capping.
In the remaining three variants, you will see different room
capping.  And if the room
rent capping is exceeded, you should know that
co-payment will be charged from the entire claim
amount.  Next feature comes friends,
pre and post hospitalization
expenses.  So, in both the plans, 60 days
of prehospitalization expenses and 180 days
of posthospitalization expenses
are covered.  Which should be related to the approved treatment claim.
And doctor
's consultation charges, medicine expenses
and diagnostic tests are also covered under this.
This reasonable number
of days will be covered under both the plans.  Next coverage is day
care treatment.  This means that it is not necessary that
we have to be admitted for 24 hours for every minor treatment.
So there are some minor surgeries
for which the procedure is completed in two to four hours.
In both the plans, these day care procedures are covered
up to the sum insured.  Now comes friends a
very important feature and that is modern
treatments.  Today, if you go to a hospital for
any treatment, every
hospital is equipped with the latest technology
and wants to provide the latest treatment to its
patients. If we
have a health insurance plan, then
why should we refuse it? The treatment is good and the
technology is latest, so its efficiency will
also be good. You will get coverage of modern treatments
in both the plans. There is
no capping on this in Optima Secure.  Whereas, the
two base variants of the Rushor 3.0 plan, i.e. Classic
and Select, have a subvention of ₹1 lakh.
But in the Elite and Black
variants, i.e. the top two variants,
it will be covered up to the sum insured.   There
is no capping or supplementation.  And now comes
home care treatment and domiciliary
treatment.  Take treatment at home.  If this
is due to some compulsion then that will be
covered under domicile treatment.  And if you take
treatment on your own, then that will be
covered under home care treatment.
This is covered under both the plans.  You must check the terms
and conditions, approval from the company and the
list of listed home care service providers.
But there is no capping on these
in both these plans.  If we talk about
road ambulance, then
ambulance may have to be used in any medical emergency.
So is there any supplementation or
any capping?  There is no such capping or sublimation in the Optima Secure plan.
But in the Ratio 3.0 plan, in the base two
variants i.e. Classic and Select,
you can claim hostelization
for road ambulance at ₹2000.  And the upper
variants i.e. Elite and Black have no
sublimit and capping on road ambulance
charges.  If we talk about air ambulance, in
Optim Secure plan you
can get coverage up to ₹5 lakh for emergency
evacuation using a registered air
ambulance service provider.  If we talk about the
Reshuffle 3.0 plan, the base two
variants, Classic and Select, do
not have the air ambulance facility.  The top
two variants, Elite and Black, have a coverage
of ₹5 lakh.  There are a total of four variants in the NVO Up Ratio 3.0 plan, the
differences in which are minor, subtle but it is
very important to understand them because our claim
depends on them.  If you
want to understand this plan in detail,
understand each and every minute difference,
compare the pricing, then
we have already made a detailed review video of Ratio 3.0.
I will give you its link
in the description of this video.
After watching this video, you
can check that out too.  So that you don't miss
any information.  Now friends, we will compare the
add ons.  This means that
we have the standard coverage of this policy, but the
add-ons will tell us how much we can modify our plan.  That is,
which plan is how flexible.  First we
will discuss the add ons of HDFC and
Optima Secure plans.  The first add-on
is critical illness.
Upon diagnosis of a listed critical illness, you
can avail a lump sum benefit ranging from ₹1 lakh to ₹5 crore.
For the treatment of your disease.  If
you have taken this add on for critical illness.
You can avail the add-on of unlimited restoration
as the
amount will be restored only once a year under the standard Optima Secure plan.
But if you
want to avail this restoration benefit unlimited times
then add on is available for this feature.
Next add on is hospital cash.  If
you want to incur some per day expenses apart from treatment, then
you can take Optima Secure plan through add-on starting from ₹500 to ₹10,000 per day.
Apart from this, the
feature of annual aggregate deductible has been given.  That means,
if you find the premium too expensive,
like if you are taking this plan for a citizen
and the premium increases too much,
then starting from ₹25,000
you can take annual aggregate deductible.
The policy will start coverage once the claim is settled after the threshold limit of deductible amount is reached in a year.
But your premiums will become
affordable.  This add-on
can compensate for higher premiums.
Next is Personal Accidental Rider.  That is,
if the adult members in the policy
die or suffer permanent total disability due to an accident, then
up to ₹1 crore can be
claimed for this loss and for this, an add-
on will have to be taken. There is an
add-on by the name of Personal Accident Writer Optimum Well Being in
which you can also avail OPD services
because
you do not get OPD coverage in the standard policy.  Apart from this,
HDFC has also recently launched some new add-ons.  The
first add-on is Parenthood,
which allows you to cover maternity expenses.  This
means that normal and C-section
delivery will also be covered in your policy.
We have already made a video about the amount of coverage and pricing of this add-on.
So you can watch that video.
I will also give you its link in the description.  The
next rider is ABCD.  This
is a very good rider under which you can cover
normal conditions like asthma, BP, diabetes for
31 days.  Because
claims related to these may also come very soon.  The
policy
holder may also need to take regular treatment.
But earlier the waiting period was 3 years,
so it was very difficult as to
who would wait for three years.  Now by paying extra premium
through ABCD Rider you can
cover the conditions from the 31st day of your
policy start.  And the final rider is
Limitless.  Limitless means you can stretch
a claim to an unlimited amount over your lifetime.
Whatever your sum
insured may be.  So if you feel
or want to have peace of mind that any
such emergency, accidental emergency or any
criticality emergency arises in which
you do not want to keep any limit on any one claim,
then you can take the rider
Limitless.  Now friends, it is the turn of
add-ons of Nepa Resh 3.0 and let us check
whether there is some innovation here or similar
riders are available.  The first rider is
Nevapa One.  This is their membership plan on which
I have already made a review video, in which
you get
priority claim service apart from some additional health tests.
Now if you want to understand in detail whether this is good or bad, then
I have also given the link of that review video
in the description.  You must
watch this video at least once.  The
next add-on is Cashback Plus.
By taking this rider, you will be
giving some extra money to the company for the time being.  But when
your renewal comes, you will get extra rewards points in this wallet, 10% on the first renewal and
then 5% of the total renewal premium.
Which you can
use in the future to
co-pay any deductible or other
associated expenses.  Tiered
network and headhash are similar add-ons.
But Headsh they have launched a new add on.
But in both cases, the company will tell you
where you have to get the treatment.  Only then will you
get the full claim.  The Headshop add-on
states that whenever you need to receive treatment,
you will call the company first.  The
company will recommend you four-five or two-three
hospitals.  If you get
treatment there, you will get full claim.  If you take
treatment outside those hospitals, there will be a
co-payment of 20%.  ₹20 will be deducted from 100.
Even if you have paid the full premium.
Similarly, tiered network is there in hospitals.
Here you are already
told the complete list of hospitals.  If you get
treatment in the list of these hospitals, you will get full claim.  If you get
treatment outside, there
is a co-payment of 20%.  But why would we impose such copayments on
ourselves?  Because in
return the company gives you some discount on premium.  The
bottom line is that if you
want the freedom to get
treatment anywhere, then you can avoid such add-ons.
But if you want a discount, you can get a
restriction imposed.  The
most important add-ons that I see within the Reshore 3.0 plan are the
add-ons that reduce the waiting period.  Here the specific
disease waiting period can be reduced from 24 months to 12
months or even 36 months.
If you reduce this waiting period
, the
company will have to pay you more premium.
But if you increase this waiting period
from 24 to 36 months for
specific diseases, then you will get some discount.
In PD waiting period,
you can reduce the waiting period of 36 months to
24 and 12 months.  You will have to pay a little more in 24 months
and if you do it for 12
months,
your premium will increase a little more.  But
you will get coverage only after the first year.  This is
good for policyholders who have a
pre-existing medical condition and
want to get coverage in their policy early.  If you do
n't want to wait for 3 years, here's the
flexibility offered in Reshore 3.0.
Apart from this, you will get personal accidental cover
and hospital cash rider under the Neva Up
Reshore 3.0 plan.  The
option of annual aggregate deductible is also available.  The
minimum annual aggregate deductible
amount is ₹10,000 and the maximum
deductible you can choose is ₹5 lakh.  Not only this,
co-payment option is also available.
That means you pay some percentage from every claim amount,
starting with 10% and maximum up
to 50%, you can choose that also.  The
company has also given five options for copayment percentage.
Now comes a very important add-on,
that is claim safeguard.  Under claim safeguard,
you get coverage for non-medical items i.e.
consumable items.
Because this expense is not covered under the standard plan.
And the most important
thing to note here is that all four lists of Ener One will be
covered here in which
maximum non-medical items
are covered.  This means that the company
cannot deduct your money from the claim for non-medical items.
Well Consult Plus is their OPD writer through which
you can avail the facilities of OPD outpatient treatment and
department
facilities.
Apart from this, you also get the add-on of Borderless in RE5 3.0.
If you
want to get treatment for a specific disease outside India, then
you can also take that as an add-on.  Or if you want to get treatment for any medical
condition
outside the Indian geographical
limits, then for that also there is a borderless add-
on which you can avail.
Your sum insured will vary depending on the variant.   The
diagnosis under the Borderless for Specified Diseases add-on must be within India.
You can get treatment anywhere.
And in this, which is completely borderless, your
diagnosis can be done outside India
and you can also get treatment outside India.
You should choose these add-ons only after reading their terms and conditions.  The
waiting period is the same for the standard versions of both the plans.  The
initial waiting period is of 30
days.  Specific diseases have a
waiting period of 24 months and PED has a
waiting period of 36 months.  But in Reshore 3.0,
you get the choice and flexibility to
reduce the waiting period for specific diseases and PEDs.  But
under the Optima Secure plan, you will definitely be able to get
coverage for some medical conditions for 31 days through the APCD rider.
Now friends, the
most important section of the video is the
price i.e. checking its premium.
Brother, I got the features.  Gave a lot of add ons.
Unlimited sum insured has been given
but it is also important to discuss how much money you will take.
So to compare the premium,
I have taken a standard family size of
two adults and two children.   The
age of adults is 38 and 35 years and the
age of children is 12 years and 10 years.
Sum insured we will try different here.
His address is New Delhi.
And first of all, let
us check the pricing of Optima Secure here.
I have added only one add-on here.  And that
is Unlimited Restoration add on in which
you will get repeated restoration
within a single year.  If this family takes a
sum insured of ₹1 lakh in Optima Secure plan,
it will cost them ₹31220
only.  The most important thing is that GST has been removed now,
so there is no GST ad.  Otherwise this
plan would have become even more expensive.  But let us
move towards higher sum insured.  So
we see coverage of ₹25 lakh.  It means ₹50 lakh
of coverage with secure benefit.
This coverage will be doubled in Secure Benefit.  So
its price, the premium for one year,
is ₹36,457
for this family.  Now let's talk about the Ratio
3.0 plan.  So I have taken the top variant which is black
because it does
not have any submit and capping in it.  There is
no such capping in Optima Secure either.
So that will be
the ideal variant to compare premium.  Add on we have
only taken one here.  That is
claim safeguard which will
cover all four lists of non-medical items.  If a
sum insured of ₹1 lakh is chosen, this
family has to pay ₹2,842.
If you choose the unlimited sum insured option,
which has no treatment limit, then
its annual premium will be
₹37,420.
Due to reduction in GST, there is a difference of Rs 6 to 7000
in the premiums.  So
that difference is also visible that now the premiums have become
quite reasonable.  Unlimited
sum insured.  So according to that the
premium is not much.  Now friends, it is time to
understand that the plans are very
good but how is the company performing in terms of claims.
Because that is what
we are buying the policy for.  Brother, if a
claim comes tomorrow, the company should not throw tantrums.   I do
n't know what all features were given in the plans.
But when a claim comes, the company
makes excuses.  So for this we will
check three metrics here.  The first one
is the claim settlement ratio and for this
we are taking the average of the data of annual reports of the last three years.
So the claim settlement ratio of HDFC Ergo has been
98%.   The
average claim settlement ratio of Neema Bhupa is 91% and here the
industry average i.e. the
claim settlement ratio in overall health insurance is
90% i.e. this is the claim settlement ratio of both the
companies which is above the industry average
but HDFC is
performing very well in terms
of claim settlement ratio i.e.
HDFC is settling the maximum number of claims out of 100.  The
next data is Incurred Claim
Ratio, which means whether the company is interested only in the money collected from the policy holder
or is it also paying the claims.
This is the ratio and comparison of these two.  The
incurred claim ratio of HDFC Ergo
is 82% which
is very good for the policy holders in the last 3 years.  If we talk about
Neema Bhupa, her average for the last
3 years is 57%, which is one of the lowest.
That means the company is getting a lot of money
but if we divide it by the
number of claims they are paying, then
that amount is not much.  But if we talk about the
industry average, then the
industry average of Unclaimed Claim Ratio is 82%, Nivapa
is much below that and the Unclaimed
Claim Ratio of HDFC is also ideal.  Our third
data scale is the number of
complaints.  Brother, we have bought the policy,
paid the money, tomorrow we will go to claim, if there is a
problem then what will we do, we will complain, if we
complain then how many complaints are being
filed in which company, the
average of complaints of HDFC Ergo for the last
three years that is seven
complaints on 10,000 claims, out of 10,000 claims only seven
complaints have been made by the policy holders.  That means the
services are very good.  Meanwhile, Neva Bupa has
43 complaints but 10,000 claims,
which is almost six times more than HDFC Ergo.
Now it is possible that HDFCR may be performing differently.
What is the industry average of complaints?  So that's only 23
complaints too.  You will find double complaints
in Neema Bhupa.  Now
we have understood and compared both these plans in detail.
Now let's
conclude the video by showing what important
points I see and how you
should look at both these plans.
So the first thing is that if we look at the features,
add-ons, flexibility, affordability,
then Nemapa Rees 3.0 has
given a tough competition to HDFC Ergo
Optima Secure Plan because here
NVPA has also kept things flexible.  Four
variants have been given.  If someone
wants a plan with capping then take the lower two variants.
If you don't want any capping or
want more coverage, you can go for the top two variants.  The
unlimited sum insured
option solves the problem that
even my sum insured of Rs 2530 lakh does
not seem sufficient to me.  So you should take a
plan with unlimited sum insured.  So, that hassle and
tension about whether your sum insured was less
or more is over.  Now there is no limit on it
and you have to pay a fixed premium.   There are
also some other small features that are
quite nice within the Reard 3.0 plan.  That is the
dependent child being older in age.
This plan can have dependent children up to 30 years,
which will make the premium more
affordable. Along with this,
all four lists of non-medical items can be covered
with add-ons, which is also a very good
feature as your out of pocket
expenses are reduced considerably at the time of claim.
But there must be something special in HDFC and GPTM Secure
that the company did
not have to launch any other plan after this plan.  This
plan is their best selling plan and
with this plan they are managing the data of such great claims.
Providing overall coverage and
service to its policy holders.
So this indicates to us
that Optima Secure is a
sustainable plan in itself.  The coverage it is providing is
also fine.  The underwriting
is fine.  The premium is also coming in well and the
company is also approving the claims very well.
Secondly, the unlimited sum
insured feature in the Reshore 3.0 plan may
look quite attractive at the moment
because there is no limit and
everyone likes freedom.  But
as this policy gets sold
more and more policy holders will take unlimited sum
insured, there are high chances of huge claims in it.
And the person who is
taking the claim may not face any problem.
But those who are not taking claims may face a
lot of problems due to the sudden increase in their premium.
That means the premium and prices of Reshore 3.0 are
reasonable right now but it does not seem that they will remain reasonable in the future also.
After comparing and analyzing all this data, these facts and these things, I understood this.
If you value brand
, legacy and great service then
you should go with HDFCGO Optima Secure
plan.  But if your choice is
flexibility with different variants with different add-ons,
you want
freedom with unlimited sum insured and you are
also looking for affordability and
low premium, then if your values
align with the Neema Reshore 3.0 plan,
then you can go with that plan.
My only
aim in making this video was to compare
both these plans for you in a completely transparent and unbiased manner
so that you can understand the
ins and outs of each plan.  Now, it is
possible that you may have many other
needs apart from this.  There may be many additional factors.
Your location, your sum insured, your
family size, medical history, many
things matter while buying a health insurance
plan.  So definitely
compare them, do research, study them.
Take your decision only after that.  You know that
currently a series is running on Insurance Impact channel
in which we are reviewing the claims data of all the health
insurance companies for the first
quarter of 2025 i.e. April, May and June
and
trying to find out which
company is performing the best
in terms of paying claims.  If you have missed that information
and have not been able to watch those videos till now, then you
can see all the data by clicking here and you will be able to know and
understand what is the condition of this company
in terms of claims.  I am Harvinder Singh.   I will meet
you in another informative video.  Till then take
care of yourself,
stay happy and stay healthy.